there we go welcome back to my computer
screen
my friend thank you very much always a
pleasure to be on your computer screen
no i think i'm on yours i like yes that
too
on your screen it's nice that might be
something less of a pleasure being on my
computer screen than being on yours
it's still a little bit flat but
the illusion works it is still a little
bit flat yes
yeah well speaking of flat it's
interesting because we were just
you you asked me how how it's going i'm
i've just uh helped my mom move from
atlanta
georgia to um to florida
and she so she she's retiring and
she moved down to her her brother and uh
and sister-in-law lived down here never
retired down here
and it's basically it's basically this
um what do you call a senior citizens
community
and
i've never really spent time in florida
um and the senior citizen community is
basically so in other words
it's it's like kind of northern
mid-state
and you could tell that there was like
nothing here and then they someone
a developer came and they
created a whole simulation of a place
and they put they put these boxes in a
row
right and they made the boxes look like
houses
and then they put like a like a senior
citizen center
right that
well each each one of these like theme
park things
um
i have to say so someone i don't know
who maybe you know who this was
you know you can always tell when a
civilization is going to collapse
because the first place it hits so you
see it in the elderly
and in the in in the children it kind of
works in from there so i i don't
take that for for what it's worth but
[Laughter]
it's um it's really something like they
they
know they have it it's it's basically
it's basically simulation right um
they had a there's a town
that they built to be um
to basically like be built for it to
look like it's from like 1800s
and it's like the whole thing this whole
town is constructed to look like
like a town center and all that kind of
stuff and then and then everyone drives
golf carts
and it's like the place is just packed
with golf carts and
old people coming here to retire
and golf and like you know like
places to golf and places to do archery
and all of this stuff um like a resort
yeah and i so i've been walking around
um and i've just been thinking to myself
okay
this is where we go to die
and i'm it i'm uh
i'm perplexed so here's usually it's
really got me thinking about some things
because
you know when we think about what a
senior citizen is
right versus or when we think about what
we mean when we say elder
right when someone's an elder and then
if someone is a senior citizen
i think they're very they connotate very
different things
there's nothing about this place right
that's that says
we've built this for for elders
this is we've definitely built this for
senior citizens
and i i think you can hear it
in a conversation i had with um and this
is nothing personal
like with my my aunt or uncle or my
nothing person i'm actually like
highlighting the possibilities that the
culture
right offers that we end up walking into
right that's more what i'm highlighting
but i like for example i listen to my
my uncle talk about the
20 minutes about how he ate his morning
dunkin donut muffin right he's like
oh yeah it's like crumbly those things
are so crumbly but boy they're good so
i got one but then i figured it out
right i turn it upside down if i turn it
upside down then it just
my aunt starts going well in my muffin
for like 25 minutes we talked about the
functionality
right of muffin hood
[Laughter]
the functionality of muffinhood
like in all the conversations all the
conversations i've peeked into
is like everybody's talking about these
logistical
concerns like as if they were
the thing to talk about right and i've
and and it struck me about i'm like what
is going on with that like
especially when you think about
when you get older right i mean
historically cultures have always
understood that it's the elders that
have
have the wisdom right and so you kind of
take care of the elders or
they have some role but they have a role
where they don't have to worry about
functioning as much
right and they get to be wise
right and here
it's interesting it's like no one's
expecting anyone to be wise
right and they aren't so therefore they
aren't expecting to be
wise right and because on some level on
one level they're taken care of but on
another level
most of them only have like maybe one
layer of family behind them
right if at all and therefore
even if they're kind of help being
helped out they're constantly having to
think about functioning because you know
as they lose capacities
right then all of a sudden all of their
attention is on this functionality
and i'm i mean
it's funny but there's something
profoundly sad about it
right it's profoundly sad about it and i
was thinking about like
you know and as i was sitting in order
to kind of you know maybe survive the
conversation let's say
oh i was sitting there thinking myself
all right what would this been
if we go back in time this conversation
right at the kitchen table what
what would have what would have been
different and i kind of put myself back
in like say
the middle ages let's say and
i kind of got it my understanding of
something like the middle ages was
you know you had your family and most
likely
we'd be sitting there with a lot more
family around
would most likely be living in the same
house or in in the same
you know buildings or something like
that and then everything that we looked
around
looked around at would have been made by
someone
right probably someone that we knew so
every every
i probably had like like you know
objects that were made by your family
before passed down i'd be probably
sitting in a chair like that that
probably has some story to it that's
connected with somebody and
and then there'd be more people but then
there'd be
like the the landowner who i would have
some relationship with right and then
there'd be
like the clergy let's say right the
who i'd have some kind of relationship
with then there'd be the church fathers
right and then the church
and so if we had that conversation on
some level when
my my uncle would speak there would be
this background
of multiple layers right of matter
on some level and i kind of got that
sense of this anxiety
that was really kind of running through
like this kind of constant sense of
alert worriedness that brings your
attention just to this
the most basics of functioning and i
said this sense because i looked at i
looked around at you know
my uncle and my aunt i was like oh
there's only one layer of family behind
them
in terms of the land that we're living
on the owner is probably some ceo to
some company that maybe
has never even been here and then
everyone around them
are elderly in the same position and so
there's like
i just got this sense it's like
on the level of protection right there's
nothing behind them or very little
behind them
or i would say even on deeper level that
in terms of
mattering right levels of mattering
right of of the consequences of my
speaking and people being concerned
about me and me and their realms of
concerns
and so i really got this sense of like
it's really weird to think about that
like growing old and you have the life
that you have
no matter how profound or significant
you are
and then you end up here
basically optimized a place optimized
for somebody's profit right and
b you're being kept entertained with
these games and
all of this stuff that are really with
people
you probably don't have much history
with and who are in the same boat as you
yet the conversation there's no
conversation around here that
it is at all speaks
mortality or death it almost speaks
something else
right but everyone knows we're old and
we're going to die
but there's it's it's spoken in the
unsaid it's spoken in the banality
of these rows of houses and these kind
of fake lawns and
so i've been um
it's just it's as a
as being guy thinking about things all
the time as i have a tendency to do
that's been that's been uh
on my mind hang on one second let me let
me adjust
i can't see you very well anymore yeah
classic i like got the light all correct
and right when it's in here my mom walks
in and closes the blinds
[Laughter]
it's like my childhood i'll play it all
over again
so is this where you are right now yeah
everything you've just described to me
you're just
you're not describing it from a distance
you're describing it from within
at this moment it just occurs to me
that's this is where you are at the
moment you're in florida
yeah okay yeah and i interesting
i was taught i talked today at a pretty
good long talk with john yesterday it
was really
it was really great um connecting with
him again
[Music]
right like what in my estimation right
i think this i think this says a lot of
things
right but one of the things that for
sure says
is that i don't because we don't have a
sense of wisdom
we don't have a sense of needing wisdom
therefore we can't see it we can't
relate to it
right therefore when someone gets old
they're a citizen a senior citizen
basically means
a citizen like you and us just
diminished
versus when you can kind of
get like perceive wisdom and understand
wisdom
like you see a you see an elder right
who's can make
some non beyond like trans rational
perceptions and choices based on things
that you could only
know through having experienced it over
and over again over a lifetime
no one's asking them those questions
they're not expecting anyone to ask them
right if anything they feel like a
burden to their kids
right and guilt around that or obligated
or whatever that is
but there is no expectation that the
life that you had lived
is of great value to anybody
and so i think on on one level it has to
do with that we
is like we don't notice that we don't
understand
or even therefore see something like
wisdom it's lost
and i was thinking about this too like
in if you go to the other end right
because we say that like if
if we look at culture right the
breakdown of an empire
right shows up in the the end of life
and the beginning of life the children
i think about like like children at
least here in america like
the public school system it's become all
about
preparing for these tests
at the end of the year in fact as far as
i can tell the grades
you know that you the grades are less
and less significant
what's more important is that like
school is to get be able to do
take these tests at the end of the year
which will predict make all kinds of
predictions about where you can go so
it's like even there
i think there's a way in which whereas
in old age the elderly
have become optimized right
to extract money from in these in these
centers
right and keeping them entertained on
some level right having
you know had just lived and like
children are
also seen as kind of a standing reserve
measure like like measuring their
abilities or their intelligence or
whatever it is
and to get the most out of their
capacities right
this sense this this sense of being able
to
sense for the for deeper conversation
about wisdom
right a deeper perception about seeing
life itself as an end in itself right
worthy of cultivating right
without not everything having to be
um immediately useful
right i think it's so lost and it's
funny when i get that
as i see that more and more and more i
understand that more i gotta
i'm just seeing it more and more places
and even down into my mom was telling me
like my
my my uncle collected
toy trains right his whole life he had
this like amazing train collection you
know the little we set up the little
villages and all that stuff
and he just had like hundreds and
hundreds of these planes like one of the
biggest collections in the world
and then he went to go sell them and
they weren't worth anything
because no one does that anymore
and then she was telling me about her my
my grandfather who had
um collected coins all his life right he
had just a whole basement full of like
old coins
she said yeah when he died and we we
we went to go sell them they weren't
worth anything because nobody collects
those things anymore
and as i was thinking about like yeah i
haven't even heard
that word hobby i never really liked
that word anyways but
but this sense in which this idleness
right
i like the sense of idling in the deeper
sense of the word
of that i i'm doing something as an end
in itself
right like collecting and those kinds of
things
that's going down as well
[Music]
so that's how i'm joking
so when you so you're there now and
how do you find so in a space that's
clearly been designed
as a kind of indefinite vacation a kind
of recreational
center by the sounds of it it's that's
why just the analogy to the resort
keeps coming to me right a place that's
designed to distract and divert
when you as someone who for whom the
space is not
intended and not designed when you
find yourself there you know when you're
not
sitting down spending time with your mom
when there isn't a very clear and
directed
activity for you to lose yourself in
how do you find yourself comporting in
that space
what do you do right so like if you're
there you're there during the day
let's say for whatever reason you're not
with your mom at any given moment in
time
how is how is guy spending his time in
this place
that is not intended for him
thinking about this like walking
literally like walking around
looking at things looking at and just
letting myself
just see it right and see more of it and
think about it
and i think when i'm
and i think on a on a on a larger scale
for me i think
one of the ways to respond to this right
and i find myself doing this a lot in
fact
in in responding in this way there's
there's an ex there's an ecstaticness
of um there's some kind of even though
the news is really bad
there is an ecstasis in the truthness
being revealed
right that sense of truth feels like
i feel like if i didn't have that i
would just be irritable and
[Music]
powerless and cynical i don't
feel that way um
and so there's a sense of where maybe
perhaps the most authentic way to be
is to really be with what is and if if
and i was thinking about what heidegger
talks about like
well you know our epoch is the time
where the being of being the sense of
the wholeness right that that
the logos gathers together right that
sense of things
is disappearing right nihilism
[Music]
to be with being is to be with its
disappearance
it's like that's the way being is
present is in its absence
it's in its knowledge yes places
right and turning towards it and like
really attempting to reveal it
there's something there's something rich
there for me
yeah and that's right that's interesting
in my family which is just they're great
people
like they're awesome like i'm enjoying
i'm enjoying
getting closer to them
[Music]
it's interesting that is
it's interesting that the the very thing
thing for lack of a better word um
that is excluded from
the givenness of the world becomes
present precisely in the margins
right of its exclusion and
i can picture you walking around in that
sort of
makeshift reality seeing precisely all
that is not there
and becoming more conversant with the
presence of what is absent
precisely for its absence um
because that is really when it becomes
more salient isn't it
when its absence becomes so perceptible
that suddenly what was given is no
longer given
and when that happens suddenly it's
revealed
yes right and so
wandering the lack thereof
is precisely the way of of
communing with it right like that's what
i'm that's that's what i'm feeling when
i listen to you sort of i can picture
you walking around there
you know looking at the the edifice of
this you know this
this resort and i can picture you seeing
precisely all that is absent from it
and walking with it despite the fact
that it is
nowhere to be found perhaps to anyone
else
yeah and in a way
as i i have that experience too when i'm
in and whether
it's whether it's in structure or in
company when i'm in
a context that lacks
the very thing that otherwise provides
vitality
in a way i feel more intimate with that
because of how noticeably absent it
might be
from a given place it's almost like a
it's almost like a reversal of the
loneliness
because it you know i was thinking about
this a lot
you know recently in the context of
loneliness and
and why a lot of people often say
that they feel far more lonely in
company or certain kinds of people
you know at least people who are who
list on the introverted side i suppose
often feel more lonely with company
than without and oftentimes i'm one of
those people
right depending on the company and
i think in some ways it's because you
know
when
when absence is appreciable
it becomes meaningful but when it's
not
but i think when it's not it's much
harder right if you feel that you really
if you feel that you are
within range of what should be apparent
of what should be meaningful but it
isn't
that to me is the lonely feeling
but when it is accounted
for in its absence to me
it's a lot less lonely so for instance
you know when you're
in a group of people
and you're very decidedly an outsider
to that group of people you know it's
like that you're you're on the opacity
side of the transparency opacity
spectrum right you're looking at this
as though you're watching a tableau from
an audience you know you're watching
something play out but you feel very
detached from it
that becomes a very meaningful
experience and so far as you suddenly
become
things become observable to you that
just never would have been
and um to me that's far
from being a lonely experience in fact
that when it's a very decisive very kind
of intelligible
dissociation and when it's one that's
kind of accounted for by the
circumstances
that detachment um can afford a kind of
inquiry that
is extremely extremely valuable and
meaningful that's kind of what i'm
hearing from you while you're there
being so on the outside
of the givenness of that world
you can read it so much more closely
than if you were really ensconced within
it
and there's something so freeing
contemplatively freeing about that
experience
right just like being in a group of
people who are all maybe
absorbed in a chattering conversation
that maybe you have no interest in
participating
but but as an observer
it becomes an incredibly meaningful
experience because suddenly you can see
the silhouette of that dialogue and you
can see precisely what it contains
and what it excludes and the difference
they're in
and um so that yeah the
i can understand i think why despite how
saddening it is
and and maybe even tragic it is there's
also a great deal of abundance to it
paradoxically to that experience
yeah yeah i really like what
i like that term that you did because it
really
it broadened the relief more that sense
of like well the opposite of that would
be something like
where there is something that is
attractive or that i want to be a part
of and somehow
i don't feel i have access to it
right right it is that kind of i mean i
think everyone knows what that feeling
is like
right yeah that's distressing right
neither your mood doesn't predispose you
to be
involved in it or like or that you're
you're
legitimately like left out you can't
find your way in
that's a very different sense
and so you know i've been thinking about
this because i
i encounter a lot of people who are
who are like like us thinking about this
right interested in this
sense of whatever is happening about
around this time in this way
you know and
there's a way in which one can one can
easily become on some sense identified
with it hopeless right
like you know depressed
consumed in some sense by the by the
nullity of the age that they're
in and i've often wondered about
what is right well what is the what is
just from a sense of one's own personal
happiness
right in a time of like you
so we'll say the apocalypse that's
coming or something right like
if this if this in fact is a time where
where
um the west doesn't decline let's say
right and the
the loss of of spirituality and the
like the emergence of nihilism
does somebody does somebody have to have
a bad mood
be in a bad mood because of it
right like is there what is the what is
a way one can be with that that's on one
really aware of it right looking right
at it
and at the same time still be enlivened
right by the fact by the way that you're
being with all of it
right because because i've often thought
about i don't know if it's on a personal
level
if i'm miserable in a miserable time
right
it doesn't necessarily i'm not sure if
that necessarily
necessarily discloses that i'm in touch
with the time
right although it's very
i can very easily like name it as that
time well i'm like depressed because you
know the apocalypse is coming
see yeah i talk about this i just start
to get brighter
[Laughter]
you're suddenly filled with angelic
light
[Laughter]
i must be a science guy liking the alpha
zone right
moving through the mass until it is
luminous
that quote like that from platinum light
streams
the mass lights it from all states
and thus
[Music]
thus was guy saying stocks suffused with
the light of the good
that's usually true anyway my friend
it's just not always uh
right analogized by the actual light
yeah this yeah that's a it's a very
very boy what a pregnant question i
think that is
um and intuitively without any kind of
qualification
it it certainly seems to me that
having your mood i think that sometimes
there is a false equivalency made
between
the trait of a particular humor
right a depressive verb like i say a
melancholic humor
um with a time of
a time of tragedy or a time when
the implicit tragedy of life is made
more pronounced
like right now that there can sometimes
be a false identity claim between an
individual bout of depressive you know
i don't know a depressive humor and that
that kind of um the macro cosmic state
of things and i think that's often
confused
and um and and i mean
we often we know we often talk about how
ecstatic and leavening
revelation is unto itself even if the
revelation is the revelation of tragedy
and suffering
the revelation thereof can often be an
ecstatic experience and i know for me
can be incredibly arousing
and leanitive insofar as it can actually
relieve
certain pains right just i mean the
the diagnosis relieves a great deal of
anxiety right
precisely because right it's diagnosis
and
i mean something as fundamental
as the recollection of tragedy
as the implicit truth of life
right that axiomatic
insight right which so so which is so
central
to so many uh of
of the canonical wisdom traditions right
buddhism maybe most explicitly but
could certainly make the argument for
christianity too right yes
a tradition whose symbol is a crucifix
right is premised on
the realization of suffering as a
prima materia right of life
and i know for me you know it's it's a
it's again for lack of a better word
it's a fact or it's a condition of life
that we do a great just like what you've
just described we do a great deal to try
and
disabuse ourselves of that memory
but i know i find that
when that memory resurfaces
sometimes precisely because it brings
it brings a great deal of lucidity and
perspective to any given problem or
situation
i find that that memory is often
rousing i find the memory is often
emboldening and encouraging rather than
deflating right the right the
recollection of the
the the sort of the recollection that
that state that that condition
is the first condition not an incidental
condition it is the first
condition and everything else
presupposes it and we forget
spend so much effort and time trying
desperately to forget
that everything else presupposes the
implicit
tragedy and suffering that is the
natural state not to be
you know not to get all you know
hobbsian about it but but you know what
i mean it's like that's that's what
we're working with fundamentally
and for me the memory of that condition
as a condition is something i find
oddly enough restorative right
i right just thinking about like the you
know
the whole second half of being in time
you know heidiger breaks down authentic
authenticity as
as a being toward death
right like like uh and i get what i get
from that is this sense in which
you turn toward like the
the impossibility of possibility right
which is what's
called death right when you turn towards
that
and in an authentic way um
this this sense of this sense of i don't
know
he calls it resoluteness right and later
later he talked about it in more
um and more like glass and height
right what that affords is
is is the particular start to shine
through right the impermanence of the
things and the profundity of somehow the
moreness
you know within things shines through
and you can start to respond to it
accordingly
right without you know being overly
attached and keeping things and all the
things that comes with
you know being robotic which i'm very
familiar with
right like yeah you're right there is
you know
it's funny because i am seeing this you
know uh
as a contrast to this that being with my
mom who i'm really proud of
like in this move right everything from
from from the from the move right
but the symbol that this move is for her
because she
you know she had um shoot she had
married
uh someone when i was let's see they got
married when i think it was in my early
20s and so they were married i don't
know
you know 12 to 20 years and he had died
about 18 months ago
and she moved to atlanta to be with him
so she kind of came to this place where
she realized
you know the very reason for my
existence down here
is with him right and so she kind of got
to this place where
you know over well not just over the
court but like with
with a lot of introspection to be able
to come to a place of
of recognizing and choosing to leave it
right with doing two things it's like it
was a genuine
being ready and strong enough to say
goodbye
to what was authentically and to move
towards a new life
and so what's interesting about this is
i feel
you know that we've been talking a lot
right and
since we've been down here and i just
get this sense of brevity from her
like like she sees all this stuff too
right so she'll probably watch this
video and matter of fact and probably
laugh her ass off right
about what we're talking about like
there is
something in her that feels very wise to
me
right and it has something it has this
transcendent
this this sense of transcendence like
there's a knowingness about
it's something like this it's something
like she'll laugh at something
right or we'll give each other a look
about something it'll just be a knowing
sense of something's funny
and there's in that laugh there's the
disclosure
of something like oh yeah
like they think that's so important
right oh like the folly right the folly
of the
of
of whatever the character neurosis that
we're looking at or the
circumstances or something like that
there's a kind of laughter that happens
that feels like wisdom it feels like i'm
drinking
in her wisdom in her sense of
transcendence
right
yeah talk about somebody who's been
through tragedy
like and i she she had a she had a
super proud of her she had a
and and and when this happened when john
died
one of the things that she keeps saying
is she's like i have
she says i have no idea i had no idea i
was
this strong and i asked her what's the
source of the strength
just like i don't know but i wouldn't
have thought that i was strong enough to
get through that
i'm here i am i'm like looking along
and it was a genuine sense of she does
she really didn't know
and that there's something about even
that that sense of strength that she's
somehow aware of
that she's not completely transparent to
herself
and she's never gonna be and actually
there's something about that that's
innate
and almost maybe even good right
and there's a there's an acceptance of
deep acceptance of that i think in her
being that has
the folly of the folly of
watching other people try to
struggle to pretend that they're
completely self-transparent or something
right
right knowing that's right that's
predisposed
right precisely through walking through
tragedy so that being said it's i notice
i'm not worried about her down here i
think she's gonna have a blast she's
gonna just
she's gonna like like she'll she'll suck
the marrow up she'll she'll
she'll they won't profit from her
good for her
is um is is
uh is your is your mom in any explicit
or implicit sense of the term
uh is she religious at all uh she grew
up lutheran
yeah i think she my grandfather took her
to church
pretty much every week she didn't do
that she didn't do that with me
um but she's also she
she got into recovery when i was 12.
both my parents did and so she got she
was her and
my my mom would be involved in like 12
steps
so she's very you know she was more
religious when she was a kid
at least around a lot more religion and
she's she's become
and she would say a lot more spiritual
right
right right right
it just it occurs to me to ask and you
and i have talked about this before that
sometimes that
that um
even if it's completely implicit
and intuitive rather than formalized
there is a certain kind of humility
that comes with the with the you know
the authentically religious disposition
that i think does help people and
precise maybe even more at that stage in
life i don't know
won't presume it but that does
help to socialize
the realization that one's life is not
one's own
you and i have talked about this before
right the realization that like not
being transparent to yourself
not being
not having the propriety over yourself
and your own life that most of us
presume to have at any given point in
time
and someone who's willing to loosen
the restraints a little bit to relax
that presumption a little bit
um also
allows herself to be surprised
yeah um allows herself to be
to be a revelation to herself
in a way that sometimes people will just
not allow
not permit not not fathom right the idea
that
even at even at the later stage of life
the idea that you can still not treat
yourself
as a feta complete i think
that there's a certain wisdom in that
humility
and um and as you're as funny as you're
talking about your mom
i think i and it's it's remarkably the
correspondence is actually quite
remarkable i think of my grandmother
who's
been through a very similar transition
in life recently
um she's in her late 80s miraculously
she's still
strong and full of vitality and very
self-sufficient
i really i truly don't know how but uh
she's quite remarkable and she's
recently made this this transition also
to a a retirement
however um you know
after you know leaving a house where
she lived for decades and that housed
was like a treasure house of memory it
basically housed
the memory of the family and the
genealogy of the family and that that
loss is something i mourned
more than she appeared to mourn it she
was remarkably
not at all very pr at least outwardly
not at all very precious about that loss
um i think that it was a greater loss
the rest of us
it would seem than it was to her but the
humility that you're describing of your
must
kind that that just for that
equilibrated perspective
that is both cannot help but be a little
burdened obviously by
the past but is ultimately looking
you know it is like jung has this jung
has this this analogy about you know the
the the temporal horizon shift when the
sun
begins its downward journey to the
horizon and in the second
half of life and he talks about sort of
the you know
the attitude of chasing the sun beneath
the horizon
and chasing it with chasing it with a
kind of renewed vitality
chasing it as though you're chasing it
through to destination
you know um keeping the momentum going
past the finish line as it were right
having that kind of
and and i sense that in her and i sense
that that's part of what you're
describing too is that it's not a
there's no it again at least outwardly
um
the interior life of a person is so hard
to know
even if and especially if it's somebody
that you love but
um it would seem to me that she's
she's chasing the sun
down into the horizon
and um
there are few there are few things in my
mind that are more impressive than that
truly you know truthfully it's funny
you know if if wisdom has something to
do with uh
a recognition that i am somehow
i can't account for myself i can't
own myself or have title to it right
if that if that starts to
if that becomes all of a sudden you
start to realize like oh
i am not as self-possessed as i thought
i don't own myself
i'm not property that i just get to
to own in some level
there's a brevity a lightness
that seems to
that that predisposes one two right
because it's like all of a sudden i
really i got that sense when you were
talking about your grandmother and this
was the case with my grandfather
and and i'm noticing it with my mom
there is a
yeah there's this essentials like like
look at this boy you know
like the fact i'm still breathing it's
just i don't know how i did that
right there's a yeah there's there's um
there's something uh it's interesting
there's something not
at stake that has never been at stake
but a recognition of
like for example she can't lose the if
you don't own your house you can't
right if you don't own the title you
can't lose it
exactly right and so there's some sense
exactly i think the pro i would imagine
the revelation
of that i'm i don't know where the title
is
right maybe no one has it but i don't
have it
it seems like just in the fact of
recognizing
that i had thought i had it whole time
but i never really even had it
seems to be access
to this brevity that just finds like
just finds oneself going for because on
some sense there's
there never was anything to lose that's
right
because it's not a thing that can be
possessed
possessed yeah right once we get over
the
the modally confused frame of it being
an object to possess
and all of a sudden we're in a territory
that's now
um it's it's uncharted by that frame
precisely because it's beyond it
and uh you know it's like the way that
we
the way that we think of our our souls
as it were right if you know
if if it is not something owned then it
is not something
that can be lost and if it's if it's um
if its propriety is is shared
and distributed between you know the
the the very very limited ego
and the the the
you know the uncharitable transcendent
then
ultimately um
then it becomes about the economy of
responsibility
it's not a shoeing responsibility but
it's understanding where the
responsibility begins
and where it ends and confers itself
unto like unto the supernal
aspect right where it where it can no
longer be accounted for it can no longer
be um it can no longer be
be reeled in anymore and i think that
people who've reached that point
and i i trust perhaps you don't have to
be you know
in the twilight of your life to reach
that point
but those who have seem to in a way
they're
you're right they're the be the the
being not unbearably
but bearably the being is a lightness to
it
yeah absolutely yeah
i'm going to turn on some more lights
here the lights yes
yeah good good idea
all right that was a that was an awesome
pause
that we just did it sure was pausing
with you
[Music]
let us unpause let us pause
so we're gonna we're gonna start on page
22. i think i think we actually read
ahead of this a bit but um
it'd be good just to backtrack just to
get kind of get our feet our feet going
again and again so this is
social context it's on the way to
language this is
a dialogue i think it's supposed to be
between
a japanese student
whose professor was a student of
heidegger's
and heidegger uh so
so basically the dialogue is basically
you know they're talking about
essentially they're talking about
language and and a lot of a lot of these
differences
of trying to trying to parse out
on something or let let
happen these these
these key terms that
that almost seem untranslatable in the
other
in the other language and so they've
been circling around this almost
impossibility in some sense of language
and as they're circling around it
the you can get the sense that the
dialogue itself starts to gather
um gather and dispose itself into some
like a different dimension almost right
that's what i got so far yep okay so
that's well said which which uh j
you'll be j yeah i'll be j so
so page 22. so i think jay 22.
you you're the japanese and i'm
and i'm i'm heidegger i think okay
here we go
and just now you mentioned the phrase
house of being
which would suggest the essence of
language
thus we have indeed stayed on the path
of the dialogue
probably only because we without quite
knowing it were obedient to what alone
according to your words allows a
dialogue to succeed
it is that undefined something
which we leave in unimpaired possession
of the voice of its promptings
what a great line yeah listen follow
this
it's that undefined something
which we leave in
possession of the voice of its prompting
you know this is great because it's it's
um
john and i thought that the next the
next four way of getting the band back
together
right with jordan and yourself and john
um is about dialogue
this sense of how dialogue the
difference between dialogue is happening
and say
narrative and the dialogue was happening
in emptiness
and what you know the inquiry into that
so this is
this really speaks to that
oh i like that i like that as a theme
yeah let's
uh yeah let's let's yeah okay let's keep
that on the docket let's keep that on
the docket
or wholeheartedly endorse that yeah
okay so we'll go ahead so um
is am i i are you up let's see
i've been i so far okay guys i'm jay
of the same
i'm sorry nope yeah the previous
okay cool at risk that this voice
in our case is silence itself
what are you thinking of now
of the same as you have in mind
of the nature of language
that is what is defining our dialogue
but even so
we must not touch it surely not
if by touching you mean grasping it in
the sense
of your european conceptualizations
no those conceptualizations are not what
i have in mind
even the phrase house of being does not
provide a concept of the nature of
language
to the great sorrow of the philosophers
who and their disgruntlement
see in such phrases no more than a decay
of thinking
aye two find much food for thought in
your phrase
house of being but on a different
grounds
i feel that it touches upon the nature
of language
without doing it injury
for if it is necessary to leave to
finding
something in full possession of its
voice
this does in no way mean that our
thinking
should not pursue the nature of language
only the manner in which the attempt
is made is decisive so that part right
there like he's making this distinction
basically between
content and process right that's the
thing that may
may be the most mattering is that it's
the way of the unfolding itself
right that if that's right on some sense
or if that's attuned on some sense
perhaps this enigmatic thing could
actually
it's undefinable something right
can maybe blossom but it's in the it's
in somehow the
the sense of the dial the process of the
dialogue itself
right i think is what's being created
right
so only in the manner of pursuit does
the thing being pursued become
meaningful
yeah the manner the meaningfulness of
the pursuit
is dependent upon the meaningfulness of
the manner of
pursuit yeah right that last part again
the meaningful the pursuit
the meaningfulness of the pursuit that
which we're pursuing
yeah it's meaningfulness is dependent
upon the manner
of the pursuit okay i think in a way
that i i think it sets exactly in a way
it's exactly what what you just said
just in different words
yeah yeah so at some level
so in the dialogue there's a couple of
other dialogues that are going on
there's like the dialogue
with the manner and the meaning right
yes in the dialogue itself that those
two things
are held right because i think this is
really just to tease us out because i
think this is probably
precisely the opposite of what would
happen in
let's say a normal dialogue or in an
idol talk or
at the dinner table or whatever right of
of that if anything if the content is
understood or listened to or wanted
if that by miracle somebody somebody's
listening but we're paying attention
right
most definitely very rarely is the
manner
of the pursuit of the conversation
at all um distinguished seen or
addressed
except that's right it remains that's
right it remains
transparent yeah yeah it remains wholly
transparent so that
the thing that distinguishes this this
dialogue or what we've been calling
dialogues is that the content always
refers back to the form
right that there is a cons so that
there's a dialogue between
form and content that actually
constitutes
the structure of the dialogue right so
that the dialogue between
guy and christopher about the content
yeah
is really uh a vessel
for the for a dialogue on another axis
which is the dialogue between the form
of dialogue
and the content that is treated by it
yeah
right yeah and and
so there's like you know so then then
the it is the form is not in this manner
of dialogue it's not
wholly transparent but of course neither
is is it wholly opaque either because
the content is still ultimately being
treated
right right if the content was not being
treated you could see that the forearm
was completely opaque because it was the
sole
focus right the form is not the sole
focus
neither is the content the sole focus
right the content is a medium for the
form
and vice versa so there's a kind of uh
there's a kind of
codependency between the two um
that equilibrates the dialogue and keeps
it evolving it's also precisely the
thing that keeps the dialogue
not static right
so i'm go as you're as you're talking
about it i noticed
like in holding all the things that you
were saying there is
kind of
[Music]
yeah and there's some kind of
transcendence that
i needed to do like a widening where
[Music]
on some level i need to have my finger
but not too heavily on either of them
because i try to it needs to become
transparent for it to work
right if i'm too much thinking about it
right
so if you're not talking about like if
you're not saying
pay attention to this pay attention to
that but it's a
the manner in which maybe it's held
right
there's a light there's a delicacy or
something that
seems to evoke a different quality of
consciousness
[Music]
it seems yes yes
especially if you're going to chew gum
at the same time
[Laughter]
shall we go on yes um
i think no no those conceptualizations
are not what i have in mind oh sorry
sorry i read that already okay sorry i'm
at the bottom of the page now
that's right only the manner in which
the attempt is made is decisive that one
line is what unfolded that uh
that little sojourn we just made okay
and so i now take courage to ask a
question which has long troubled me
and which your visit now almost compels
me to ask do not count too heavily
on my powers to follow your question
our dialogue meanwhile has anyhow
made me much more aware of how
unthought everything still is
that concerns the nature of language
[Music]
and especially since the nature of
language remains something altogether
different for the east asian and the
european peoples
and what you call nature
also remains different how
then could our reflection get out into
the open
[Music]
most easily if from the very outset we
do not demand too much
thus i shall permit myself for the
moment to put to you
an altogether preliminary question
i fear that even this question can
hardly be
answered unless we we disregard the
danger
of our dialogue so just like this this
is still the questions unasked right
so i think is this would you say chris
is this
carefulness right
is that yes it definitely is that
at least that right that carefulness if
we look at the if you read this whole
thing as
also reading the manner in which this
dialogue was happening right
that careful yeah yeah they're trying to
it's like they're trying to furnish the
world
in which the question is going to live
right it's very socratic thing to do and
they're trying to take care to furnish
it in such a way that the question when
it enters the world
will will will be able
to live comfortably within the world or
perhaps
not all together comfortably right so
they're trying to set the conditions
that the question is going to
to to it to sort of
like the the
the question will become
the fulcrum it'll become the center
of a cosmos and what they're trying to
do is they're trying
to fit figure and furnish the cosmos
so that it can seed the focus to the
central question
but also be prepared to expand it it's
the habitus for the question
that they're trying to gather together
right it's like they're trying to make a
nest
so that when they place this delicate
egg into the nest
it actually is going to be able to hatch
and fly right right so they're
they're they're dialogue i think is what
they're doing
right by doing this right and we i mean
i've catch myself
in in you know in in other contexts
doing
very much the same thing i'm sure you do
too right when you know you're about
whether whether whether personally or
impersonally
when you're about to introduce something
that's going to be volatile
philosophically volatile or emotionally
volatile whatever the nature of the
volatility
when you're introducing a question
that's going to be volatile
you want to um
you want to make sure that you're you
are
you're you're
it's like you have to you have to
enculturate
this the setting into which it's going
to grow
and if you don't do that properly or
sometimes the feeling is when you don't
do that properly
then really you're going to you're going
to set it up to
to fail and so i think that's part of
the reason for the carefulness
they're trying to they're trying to tune
the settings so that when they introduce
this new melody that it doesn't simply
it's not simply
engulfed and it doesn't simply dominate
but that it cohabitates
in the conversation in such a way that
allows it to grow
properly right anyway
here between like
in some sense they're furnishing the
possibility
of addressing and bringing this in
but yeah but the reason one of the
reasons why they're so careful about it
it seems is because how little
an awareness of how well at one level
how important it
is but like how much they don't know
yeah exactly they don't know what it's
going to become
for what somebody profoundly understand
that they don't know
so one pun furnish right
a environment or a world
[Music]
for something that you clearly
respectfully don't know about
right on sales it's a very it's a that's
really interesting in itself just
uh well that's that's kind of part of
the thing that we're
in dialogues it's precisely that's the
kind of thing
that's yeah i'm starting now i'm
starting to hear the logos of this
yes right yes especially that sense in
which um
is that fragment that i i talked about
in my chapter the
do not listen to me right
instead gather yourself in the gathering
itself right right in fitting knowledge
one tones all right
that is the most hide and green twist of
heraclitus i've ever heard
right so interesting
yeah because it's like you want the form
you want to you want to um
you want to socialize the form so that
it can
seed its territory to the content but
not also
be overwhelmed by the content and
dissolve altogether
right so you want the form to be
flexible elastic enough
that it's going to be able to morph
itself
around the gathering content of the
dialogue but you also don't want the
form to dissolve because if the form
dissolves all together
then all of a sudden there is nothing to
gather anymore because
that which is gathered has to actually
be
gathered within a container
a container that is that is a
that is elastic enough to allow the
gathering to evolve and to grow
but that is substantial enough
not to lose the content and have it
scatter and become dissolute
right so that so that it has to be again
it's that
it has to it has to be able to expand
but also to contract back
yeah right
so interesting when you know especially
when they're basically saying
what happens if we prepare the house
language itself right
we're both we're both preparing the
house and furnishing the house
for the category of house
to be housed in this the content of
housing
right this is uh yes
dyslexia loves this
yeah you're you're uh you deal with that
very very
admirably i have to say like you
you wade right in there you soldier
through and you do it very well and i
and i i think it's uh yeah just
i yeah it's very impressive that's very
impressive
i've never been compliments to you my
friend
well it's it's not i mean it's it's for
the for people
like me who don't experience it it's a
very easy thing to forget
and to ignore because it's just not like
to me it's not a salient detail and i
have to sometimes remind myself or have
you remind me
um and um and as soon as i
become aware again that you're
like the the the the sort of the default
conditions
through which you're interacting with
this are so different
yeah that immediately is becomes an
interesting
detail and an admirable one considering
how
um how how boldly you venture into it
so you're right on thank you um
okay so we're right where did we leave
over here most easily from the very outs
that we do demand
oh yes so i just i just finished saying
um that's official permit myself for the
moment to put to you an altogether
preliminary question
we're about halfway down yeah or sorry
not
no less less than halfway down
[Music]
i'll tell you what let's just start
how then could our reflection
get out into the open
most easily if from the very outset we
do not demand too much
thus i shall permit myself for the
moment to put to you an altogether
preliminary question
i fear that even this question can
hardly be
answered unless we disregard the danger
of our dialogue that cannot be
since we are walking toward the danger
and ask away after all that
after all that right after all that
there's this implicit agreement okay at
this point we've
we've we've pre-figured we've
pre-figured the conversational world
enough that when we throw this into
it it probably probably yes certainly
but probably won't
implode and devour us yeah the
the ancient greek name for that is
[Music]
[ __ ]
yes [ __ ] it exactly
and ask your daddy okay and ask away
okay what does the japanese world
understand by language asked
still more cautiously do you have in
your language
a word for what we call language if not
how do you experience what with us is
called language
no one has ever ever asked me that
question before
and it seems to me also
that we in our in our own japanese world
pay no heed to what you are asking
asking me now i must beg you
then to allow me a few moments of
reflection
okay so this makes me giddy because
philosophical dialogues never have stage
directions
and so when there's actually a stage
direction and a philosophical dialogue i
just that
that's right i think that's music i love
it i love it so the stage direction is
the japanese closes his eyes
lowers his head and sinks into a long
reflection
the enquirer waits until his guest
resumes the conversation
okay so you you sink into your
reflection now guy
and uh and i'll wait okay
[Laughter]
there is a japanese word
that says the essential being of
language
rather than being of use as a name for
speaking
and for language
[Music]
the matter itself requires that because
the essential
being of language cannot be anything
linguistic
the same holds truth but the phrase
house of being from a great distance
i sense a kinship between our word
that is now before my mind in your
phrase
[Music]
the phrase gives a hint of the nature of
language
it seems to me that you have just said a
freeing word
then that hint would be the word's
basic character oh okay let's pause
there
okay let's pause there that's
interesting yeah
that's interesting so a freeing word
so the word itself the
the the t loss of the word right the the
word
the the direction of the spokenness of
the word
is what he's here referring to as the
character of the word
and that's interesting right it's the
direction of the speech
it's that into which
it is that into which the word
is spoken that is the word's character
or interesting right interest right so
there's this
this adverbial nature then
to the spoken word right because the
it's
freeing it's it's literally verbalized
right
the word is freeing and that and the
and that
which makes the word
no what am i trying to say it's
it's it's it's the i mean fundamentally
it's it's
it's it's the logos of the word right
it's the structural
functional organization and direction of
the word
that gives it its character so i think
in a way what's being said here is
that is that what they're seeing behind
the word
is the logos of its intent the logos of
its function
right right cc then that hint would be
the words
basic character the hint i think
the hint is the the glimpse of the logos
that emerges when the direction
of the word speech is revealed in the
dialogue
that's why the dialogue that's why
dialogos
becomes a way of glimpsing logos
within word because dialogos directs
speech right and it is the
direction of speech the direction
of the word which is its verbal function
right which reveals its character or
its logos yeah is it is it is it is it
fancy
to talk about that in terms of
the the character the word is
in some sense is the possibility
that it's addressing right yes yes
hiddenness to that possibility is
revealed and so on some level we can be
in that direction but yet that
possibility that it's revealing its
direction
its character hasn't yet been fully
disclosed to us
that's right but then it can be
and then we can have that experience of
like oh we've been
inside of this this character this
possibility
without knowing it the whole like for
the last five minutes
but then it becomes clear exactly yeah
i think that's exactly it i think it's a
great way of putting it it's like the
the it is the word has a want that
strives and the striving
the striving of the word is is its
is its attention as you say is his
attention to possibility
it adverts itself to possibility and
strives and what's the nature of the
striving of the word
and that only becomes observable i think
in when the word is allowed to strive
in in direction and it's allowed to
strive in direction
when it is directed to the comprehension
of the listening ear
right and so the word takes on
some of the valence of the logos and the
verbal nature of the logos
when spoken in to the comprehension of
dialogue which
is why there is an implicit dramaturgy
the logos the chara like the word
carragher we talked about this several
times but like
i can't i i feel like i'm becoming
obsessive about
that the understanding character as
being understanding character
as the as as the most proximate way of
understanding the logos
right there's that and most proximate
because not identical
not identical still analogized but yeah
it seems to you know right and i think i
think one of the things
of maybe why this is being highlighted
in the way that it is
is it i think like the normal
understanding of
a direction is something that you choose
to take
it does it has this will quality from
the subject
right towards the direction but this is
talking
this is coming from a very different
place it's saying that no
we're following something right in fact
the direction the character the word
will come
after we're already have followed it
right
so it's not a will right
of a direction but it's a list so this
is really as much about listening
this dialogue when it is about
saying something right this is on some
levels this is like
verbally articulating the way one
listens to the character
of the unfolding happening right there's
that right
that light touch throughout right of
course i really i can't i can feel the
japanese spirit of that big time
ah yeah yeah
which is why the way that the dialogue
is framed is is
it allow allows for that precisely
because the
he's like he's using he's using the
translation of culture
as a way of understanding the
translation of the logos
yeah oh man i don't want i don't want
this to end
ever and i have my meeting at seven
so well that's right okay all right i'll
uh
okay awesome i'll let you i'll let you
go this is a very hard this was great
this is great and it's been a while so
this is it's oh yeah doubly dub
it's doubly a pleasure for the fact that
it's been a little while
much love my friend no much left to you
we'll do this soon
bye